{
  "lessonId": "lesson16",
  "lessonTitle": "Урок 16",
  "lessonDescription": "Як to be чи не to be у present Simple",
  "lessonURL": "",
  "lessonItems": [
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "I am not <i> We,you,they are not (aren't) </i> He,she,it is not (isn't)",
      "startTime": "1:05"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "Am I...? <i> Are we,you,they...?</i> Is he,she,it...?",
      "startTime": "2:27"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Я - не лікар",
      "answer":   "I am not a doctor",
      "startTime": "2:35"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Я - не в (цій) сільській місцевості",
      "answer":   "I am not in the countryside",
      "startTime": "2:50"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ми - не німецькі (ці) студенти",
      "answer":   "We are not the German students",
      "startTime": "3:06"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ми - не в музеї",
      "answer":   "We aren't in a museum",
      "startTime": "3:18"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вони - не в місті",
      "answer":   "They are not in a city",
      "startTime": "3:33"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вони - не фотографи",
      "answer":   "They aren't photographers",
      "startTime": "3:43"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти - не в офісі",
      "answer":   "You are not in an office",
      "startTime": "3:53"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>sad</b> /sæd/ сумний",
      "startTime": "4:05"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти - не сумний",
      "answer":   "You aren't sad",
      "startTime": "4:22"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він - не поліцейський",
      "answer":   "He is not a policeman",
      "startTime": "4:32"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він - не вдома",
      "answer":   "He isn't at home",
      "startTime": "4:41"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вона - не медсестра",
      "answer":   "She is not a nurse",
      "startTime": "5:29"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вона - не в театрі",
      "answer":   "She isn't in a theatre",
      "startTime": "5:49"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Це - не помилка",
      "answer":   "It is not a mistake",
      "startTime": "6:00"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Це - не теплий вечір",
      "answer":   "It isn't a warm evening",
      "startTime": "6:12"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Я - не на роботі",
      "answer":   "I am not at work",
      "startTime": "6:23"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вони - не біля моря",
      "answer":   "They aren't at the seaside",
      "startTime": "6:36"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ми - не в Харкові (Kharkiv)",
      "answer":   "We aren't in Kharkiv",
      "startTime": "6:53"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>visitor</b> /ˈvɪzɪtə/ відвідувач",
      "startTime": "7:01"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він - не відвідувач",
      "answer":   "He isn't a visitor",
      "startTime": "7:04"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>player</b> /ˈpleɪə(ɹ)/ гравець",
      "startTime": "7:26"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вони - не гравці",
      "answer":   "They aren't players",
      "startTime": "7:28"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>dictionary</b> /ˈdɪkʃənɛɹi/ словник",
      "startTime": "7:39"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Це - не словник",
      "answer":   "It isn't a dictionary",
      "startTime": "8:06"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Я - на Воттс Стріт (Watts Street)?",
      "answer":   "Am I in Watts Street?",
      "startTime": "9:20"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "Перед назвою вулиці ставимо IN",
      "startTime": "9:45"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ми - у бібліотеці?",
      "answer":   "Are we in the library?",
      "startTime": "10:00"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти - голодний?",
      "answer":   "Are you hungry?",
      "startTime": "10:08"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>stadium</b> /ˈsteɪ.di.əm/ стадіон",
      "startTime": "10:21"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вони - на стадіоні Вімблдон (Wimbledon Stadium)?",
      "answer":   "Are they at Wimbledon Stadium?",
      "startTime": "10:29"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Це - твоє хобі?",
      "answer":   "Is it your hobby?",
      "startTime": "10:38"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>ready</b> /ˈɹɛdi/ бути готовим",
      "startTime": "10:44"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він - готовий до спілкування?",
      "answer":   "Is he ready for communication?",
      "startTime": "10:47"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>brave</b> /bɹeɪv/ хоробрий",
      "startTime": "10:58"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вона - хоробра?",
      "answer":   "Is she brave?",
      "startTime": "11:08"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>kind</b> /kaɪnd/ добрий",
      "startTime": "11:15"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти - добрий?",
      "answer":   "Are you kind?",
      "startTime": "11:18"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Цей чоловік - студент?",
      "answer":   "Is the man a student?",
      "startTime": "11:25"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ми - щасливі?",
      "answer":   "Are we happy?",
      "startTime": "11:33"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Джейн (Jane) - письменниця?",
      "answer":   "Is Jane a writer?",
      "startTime": "12:29"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>those</b> /ðoʊz/ ті",
      "startTime": "12:43"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ті люди - науковці?",
      "answer":   "Are those people the scientists?",
      "startTime": "12:56"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Це - твій блог?",
      "answer":   "Is it your blog?",
      "startTime": "13:15"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>hot</b> /hɑt/ жарко, жаркий",
      "startTime": "13:23"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Йому - жарко?",
      "answer":   "Is he hot?",
      "startTime": "13:35"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Це - обід?",
      "answer":   "Is it the afternoon?",
      "startTime": "13:44"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти - у школі?",
      "answer":   "Are you at school?",
      "startTime": "13:55"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>present</b> /ˈpɹɛzənt/ подарунок, простий",
      "startTime": "13:58"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Це - подарунок?",
      "answer":   "Is it a present?",
      "startTime": "14:00"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Твій тато - в аеропорті?",
      "answer":   "Is your dad at the airport?",
      "startTime": "14:09"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>singer</b> /ˈsɪŋə/ співак",
      "startTime": "15:37"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ден (Dan) - не співак",
      "answer":   "Dan isn't a singer",
      "startTime": "15:41"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>flower</b> /ˈflaʊ.ə/ квітка",
      "startTime": "15:49"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Це - квітка?",
      "answer":   "Is it a flower?",
      "startTime": "15:50"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>way</b> /weɪ/ шлях, дорога, путь",
      "startTime": "15:55"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Це - шлях?",
      "answer":   "Is it a way?",
      "startTime": "15:57"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>angry</b> /ˈæŋ.ɡɹi/ злий, сердитий",
      "startTime": "16:12"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Моя мама - не зла",
      "answer":   "My mum isn't angry",
      "startTime": "16:20"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>lovely</b> /ˈlʌvli/ чудовий, милий",
      "startTime": "16:28"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вона - добра і мила?",
      "answer":   "Is she kind and lovely?",
      "startTime": "16:29"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>role-model</b> зразок для наслідування",
      "startTime": "16:48"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти - зразок для наслідування?",
      "answer":   "Are you a role-model?",
      "startTime": "16:50"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Це - весело?",
      "answer":   "Is it fun?",
      "startTime": "16:58"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>dancer</b> /ˈdɑːns.ə(ɹ)/ танцівник, танцівниця",
      "startTime": "17:04"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Мої сестри - не танцівниці",
      "answer":   "My sisters aren't dancers",
      "startTime": "17:07"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>Friday</b> /ˈfɹaɪdeɪ/ п'ятниця",
      "startTime": "17:17"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Cьогодні - не п'ятниця",
      "answer":   "It isn't Friday today",
      "startTime": "17:42"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вони - на роботі?",
      "answer":   "Are they at work?",
      "startTime": "17:51"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ми - не в кафе",
      "answer":   "We aren't in a cafe",
      "startTime": "17:57"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>bar</b> /bɑː/, /bɑɹ/ шматок, плитка",
      "startTime": "18:47"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Це - не шоколадна плитка",
      "answer":   "It isn't a chocolate bar",
      "startTime": "19:08"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>winner</b> /ˈwɪnə/ переможець",
      "startTime": "19:16"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти - спортивний переможець?",
      "answer":   "Are you a sport winner?",
      "startTime": "19:18"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>midnight</b> /ˈmɪdnʌɪt/ північ",
      "startTime": "19:31"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Це - не північ",
      "answer":   "It isn't a midnight",
      "startTime": "19:48"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Діана (Diana) - в Індії (India)?",
      "answer":   "Is Diana in India?",
      "startTime": "19:58"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>sunny</b> /ˈsʌni/ сонячний",
      "startTime": "20:08"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Погода - не сонячна",
      "answer":   "The weather isn't sunny",
      "startTime": "20:10"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>task</b> /tɑːsk/ завдання",
      "startTime": "20:23"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ми - не готові до цього завдання",
      "answer":   "We aren't ready for this task",
      "startTime": "20:33"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>thing</b> /θɪŋ/ річ",
      "startTime": "20:41"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ці речі - не його",
      "answer":   "These things aren't his",
      "startTime": "20:56"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ця парасолька - не її",
      "answer":   "This umbrella isn't her",
      "startTime": "21:19"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Це - довга подорож?",
      "answer":   "Is it a long journey?",
      "startTime": "21:46"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>go on</b> продовжувати",
      "startTime": "21:58"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти - готовий до продовження?",
      "answer":   "Are you ready to go on?",
      "startTime": "22:09"
    }
  ]
}
